How to Create an Affinity Reflowable EPUB with Custom CSS Styles that works on Amazon

Step 1: Creating an Affinity EPUB Template and CSS File

Open the Affinity App, and create a new RGB document. I like the A5 size since it looks a bit like a tablet, but any size technically works.
For the sake of time, I'll point you to a couple handy Canva training videos on how to do this in the new Affinity version. I watched this one for the basics. https://youtu.be/a9cHSsA3PdE. The process works. I use a Master Page, however, as you will see in this document.
NOTE: if you are going to have any images or glyphs in your book, you may want a resolution greater than 72 for the sake of image quality, but keep it below 144 dpi. Amazon shrinks images that are too big. If you aren’t using ornate headers, 72 dpi works pretty well.
Take a minute and set up your text styles.
Make sure you have licenses for your fonts, or you are using freely available commercial fonts. This does actually matter when you are publishing for sale on Amazon.

NOTE: If you have a finished manuscript that is already formatted in, say, Word, you can actually have Affinity pull your existing formatting in as styles, and they will pop up in your Text Styles panel. This can be useful because… well, just keep going and you’ll figure out why. It works just starting from scratch, too, but this can be an easy way to format while you set things up.

Copy and paste some text into the text box on page one if you need to see what it all looks like. I highly recommend using this initial document as a way to set up a template that you can use over and over again. It will save you time. Anywho.
Get your text styles ready. Using Paragraph Styles, format your chapter headings and and chapter subtitles, set up your body text and any special block text styles.example: your main character has written a letter to her love interest, and you want a large block of specially indented italicized text, or you’re quoting a poem and want it centered. Just make a text style with that formatting, and use it on that block of text. Paragraph styles are not for one-off inline text style changes like an italicized word here and there. That’s a character style (the ‘a’).

Tip: As you work, you may want to name all of your own styles something that you can recognize later. Some signal to yourself that it’s yours.

Also create a few character styles. (the 'a' in the text styles panel as opposed to the P).
You may want to set one for Inline Italics because I found that the CSS won't include it otherwise. You can do this by simply highlighting some of your main body text, toggling the Italics on the text box toolbar, then going to your text styles panel and adding the character style with the +a option. Select 'no change' for all the font options, and you can use that character format on any inline text in the document without changing the size of the font or the font itself. Make sure Italics is selected on the Text Style Editor panel's Font section. It’ll be a little button below the style options. If you just use the text box tool italics, or the command+i keyboard shortcut to style a bit of text in your document, it won't transfer into the EPUB when you export. Go on. Ask me how I know. For this, you have to have a character style that can be exported just for that purpose.

Tip: rather than going through your entire document one page at a time, an “easy” way to make sure all of the special character styles in your document are painted with the character styles you’ve created in your template, you can use Find and Replace to search for Format: Italics (or whichever special style). It will highlight ALL of the italicized text (which might be more than you wanted) but you can then go down the list and Replace (or skip an unwanted instance by pressing the find button again) with Style: Inline Italics or whatever you’ve called it. Fiddly? Yes. But that’s what formatting is. Fiddling.

IF YOU WANT THE POSH CUSTOM DROP CAP COVETED BY PENNILESS INDIE WRITERS EVERYWHERE: It works beautifully! I love this part.
Ok. First, create a character style for your Drop Cap. It doesn't have to look pretty, it just has to be there. You can tweak it in the CSS later, but it's important to have this set up. For the sake of looks in your affinity document, though, I suggest you edit it to look like what you want, font, style, etc. You're not using the Drop Cap option in the text styles editor yet, you're just creating a character style, so size, variants, etc.
Also, keep in mind that a lot of reading devices allow the reader to set their own preferences for font family, so all you’re really doing is telling their phone to show a drop cap. But, some people (me) like to show the original formatting, so that’s where it’s good to be a little picky, here.

Now you go in and get your chapter’s first paragraph formatted:

Create a Paragraph Style: One way to do this is in the Text Styles Editor. In Style, select your desired options for style to base it on, if any, and whether or not you want a specific text style or level to follow it. I usually base it on Normal, or whatever I've called my Body Text style, and follow it with Normal.
Under Character select your desired font, text size,etc. A good rule of thumb is to keep it the same as the rest of the body text so it blends nicely.
Then in Spacing, select 'justified last line left.'
In Paragraph, go to Drop Caps, and enable the Drop Cap. 3 lines is good, and you want left align and scale for descenders. Give a little space to text. For the 'style' option, click the arrow and you'll see your Drop Cap character style in the dropdown. Select that, and voila.
Repeat the character style creation step if you want an Initial Words setting - as in the first few words of your first paragraphs are in small caps, or italicized caps. Whatever. You’ll need a character style for that, but it works very much the same as the Drop Cap. So create the character style first, then use it in your First Paragraph Paragraph Style formatting.
Click OK.
Select your first paragraph and apply First Paragraph formatting.
THIS WILL AUTOMATICALLY-LIKE-MAGIC INSERT A DROP CAP (and any other formatting options) into your first paragraph as you go through and format your chapters. Which is AWESOME. Sorry. I’ve been working with Word so long this is still making me geek out, and if you’ve ever tried to insert Drop Caps into a 40 chapter Word document, you will understand.

Next you're going to:

Place your chapter header images and pin them as INLINE using the Pinning panel. The videos and all the Canva suggestions I found for creating these seem to want them to float with text, but it is a PAIN in the BOTOX to mess with in the Affinity document. Just saying. Inline actually works too, and I had no trouble with it reflowing in the finished product.
Also rasterize your images. This makes them adopt the same dpi as your document, and you won't wind up being surprised by tiny, underwhelming images in your finished Kindle Book.

You may want to set up a Text Style just for those images, which can be useful in finding them all later. I went ahead and created a Glyph and a Header Image text style so I could easily navigate to any of them and swap them if necessary. Find and Replace is sort of your document navigation, I’ve found.

If you’re working on your manuscript, now is a good time to go through and format everything using only the text styles you’ve created.

Finishing Up:

NOW: Delete all the other unused not-yours styles. I mean it. Get rid of them. Anything that isn't being used, cut it off.
THEN: On the Text Styles panel, right click the ‘hamburger’ for each Paragraph Style that is being used, select 'edit style'
In the Text Style Editor, go down to Export Tags, and under EPUB, select Include Class in HTML and Emit CSS.
You will also want to select 'p' for any paragraph/body styles, and 'h1' 'h2' etc. for any title and subtitle hierarchy.
ALSO: Right click each of your Character Styles, go to Edit Style, and do the same in Export Tags with the Include Class in HTML and Emit CSS, but this time you want to select 'span' so that they are applied only to inline text as style options.

Alright. Your template should be good to go at this point, so you want to:

Export as an EPUB. You'll see the Export options panel on the right. You don't have to worry about any of the options EXCEPT Generate CSS from Styles. Keep that checked. And maybe check Show in Finder. That just comes in handy.
You could also take a moment to save your document as a template and an AF file under whatever name you want, as well.

The reason you exported this as an EPUB with CSS generated from styles is simply so you can get that CSS with your isolated chosen text styles, because...

Step 2: Creating a Custom CSS Stylesheet

Open your CSS editor.

Use the Open menu to open your EPUB document. It will import all of your CSS, and if it's anything like Sigil, it may throw a fit because Affinity does weird things with CSS generation at the moment. Maybe they will get this fixed. If the Higher Ups are reading this, I might suggest having some sort of CSS editor built into the Affinity wardrobe. You can create it but it's hidden at the moment, and not editable.

Alright. You've got your EPUB's guts on the table. You want to find your Text Stylesheet. In Sigil, this is in the Styles folder in the left-hand navigation panel, under Text. Open that sucker.
Select whatever file ends in Styles.css.
Then refrain from freaking out.
You're going to find a ton of styles in there that aren't actually in your document.
A few at the top with @font-face { in the title will be the ones that you want in your document. You can keep those there, since that tells the reader what font you're using. But you can delete any of the fonts that you don't want to use - there may be a few.
Then, wade into your paragraph and span styles. If it has coding but isn't on your list of created styles: go ahead and get rid of it. (Gasp!). I swear, the CSS will still work. There will probably be a whole bunch of 'p' styles with nothing, and maybe some empty 'span' styles, and extra headings. Whatever. If it's not in your document, cut it off.
Now go in and find the ones that you created, used, and named. They'll be recognizable, and they will be there amid the chaos.
Edit your code.

I found that if I wanted the paragraphs not to have a space between them on an Ereader, I had to go in and find my body paragraph styles, and add the line margin-bottom:0; to the code. (Copy only the highlighted selection). That line was not included in the code that came over from Affinity. I do not know why. Sigil may have 'cleaned' it. I only know how to work around it if it's not in there.
I also found upon validating the code out that there will be incorrect widows and orphans code. The code needs to have a value of something greater than zero. So that part of the code would go: widows:1; orphans:1; Which would keep one line at the top of the page, and a single line at the bottom. You can have anything more than one, but it can't be 0.
Below is the Drop Cap Code I used. (My Character Style was called, get this: Drop Cap.)

.Drop_Cap {

font-family:Garamond, serif;

float:left;

font-size:450.0%;

line-height:.75;

margin-right:.03em;

}

You can copy and paste that (copy everything that's highlighted blue) into your own CSS and twiddle with it however you want, rename it to your Drop Cap Style Name, change the font, whatever. These settings transfer well into the EPUB reader as a 3 line drop cap.

Note: I couldn't figure out how to force the reader to only display the font I wanted for the title and the drop cap. This is a feature I've seen on some really pretty eBooks, and I'd love to figure it out, but it seems to require going through the entire document's CSS text to add a specific command to the text formatting that tells it to show the drop cap as 'font:"whatever"' in that paragraph. If anyone has any suggestions for this, let me know!

Right. So. You've tweaked your CSS Stylesheet.

Now save just that sheet.

In Sigil, you can right-click on the Styles.css menu item that you opened, and it will give you a drop down with a save-as option - I recommend putting it in the same folder with your template, but you do you.

To add this to your Affinity document:

Open your EPUB panel. (Click the down arrow on any tab full of panels, and select ‘panels,’ then select ‘EPUB.’)
Make sure the Embed on Add option is toggled on, and add the CSS file you just created.NOTE: The stylesheet doesn't actually follow your template, so you'll have to add it to any finished book, but now you've got one that works, and that you can adapt to whatever you need.

Step 3: Creating your Reflowable EPUB with your specialty Embedded CSS Stylesheet

You can use the template now, and just copy and paste your manuscript into your text box on your first page and then click the autoflow arrow. (See video link mentioned above for more in-depth instructions.)

This is where it can get hairy. If your text is already formatted in your text processor, Affinity can bring those formatting options in as styles - which, as mentioned above, you can use to create your initial text styles in your template. You can also opt to keep or replace the Affinity styles. But keep in mind that however you choose to go about creating your text style collection, the names of the styles in use in your document have to match the CSS file exactly because that's what tells the EPUB reader to display the styles you've selected.

Side-note: Pasting unformatted text gets rid of any chapter headings you had, which makes navigation a pain. If I was bringing my text into an Affinity document created with the template, I found it was easier to have some headings set up in my initial word editing document before pasting into Affinity, then go through and use the Find and Replace panel to find all of those word processor styles and switch them to my Template/CSS styles using the Replace: Styles feature. That way I could be sure it was the right style name/format. (I hope that was understandable.)

Begin formatting your document using the styles you created.

Don’t forget to use your inline character styles instead of the text box styles for inline bold, italics, and underline.

You will want to create your ToC, any front and back matter, etc now. Have your cover image ready to go as well. There are videos and instructions on Canva for most of these things.

NOTE: I made my own ToC using anchors and links, which is how you have to do it in Word, but there is a ToC panel available in Affinity. Maybe someone could test that out and see how it works in CSS. The Table of Contents I made using links and anchors in Affinity works perfectly on Amazon, but it’s maybe not as simple to create as the automatic ToC generator.

Once you have your whole document formatted and ready to go (which is the nitty-gritty fiddly part, so buckle in for a day of clicking mouse buttons) you can export it as your official reflowable EPUB.

To do this, here are a few helpful hints.

In the EPUB Reflowable Export panel, this time you want to do the following, where X indicates an unused option or a NOT:

Use Document Resolution

X Downsample

Compression: 100

X Convert Bulleted

X Convert Numbered Lists

Remove line breaks

X Generate CSS from Styles

X Preserve Local Overrides

X Hide TOC Numbers

Cover Page: Use cover image from file

Pagination Source: None

Ask for Location/ Show in finder

You don’t need to generate another CSS file, you want the Ereader to pick up the one you’ve embedded. If you preserve local overrides, it seems to favor the Ereader’s settings more than the CSS file. I may be wrong about this, but it doesn't change the usability when it's not checked.

Then:

Export.
Name your file.
Check your work using your own Ereader, like Books on iMac.

Further Resources

All in all, I think I used the following Paragraph and Character Styles, just as an example:

Paragraph:

Chapter Number

Chapter Header

Centered Glyph

Centered Header

Journal Entry Date

First Paragraph w Drop Cap

First Paragraph No Drop Cap

Normal Body Text

Letter Indent Italics

Centered Poetry Italics

Centered Normal

Centered Bold

Table of Contents

Character:

Inline Italics

Drop Cap

Initial Words

Hyperlink

There are a few of these in the Text Styles for this Document for reference that you can edit if you want and practice exporting for a CSS Sheet.